Polish Survivors of the Holocaust: an oral history project 1980-1982 CPAA 96-01
Connecticut Polish American Archives, Elihu Burritt Library, Central Connecticut State University, New Britain
Polish Survivors of the Holocaust: an oral history project
1978-1987 (Bulk 1980-1982)
Stanislaus A. Blejwas
CPAA 96-01
11 boxes (5 linear ft.)
Connecticut Polish American Archives, Elihu Burritt Library, Central Connecticut State University
Polish Survivors of the Holocaust, an oral history project was initiated by Prof. Stanislaus A. Blejwas from Central Connecticut State College and co-sponsored by the Association of Polish Priests in Connecticut. The project was funded by the Connecticut Humanities Council. Parts of the interviews were broadcasted in a miniseries at the Connecticut Public Radio. All interviews were transcribed. Collection contains documentation of the project, related correspondence and various publications on Polish Jewish relations and teaching the Holocaust. Collection illustrates experience of non-Jewish survivors of the Nazi concentration camps in World War II, who immigrated to the US and lived in Connecticut.
Historical/Biographical Note
Polish Survivors of the Holocaust: an oral history project was sponsored by the grant from the Connecticut Humanities Council and several Polish American organizations. The project was proposed by Prof. Stanislaus Blejwas, from the department of History at Central Connecticut State College and Msgr. John Wodarski, pastor of the Holy Cross church representing the Association of Polish Priests in Connecticut. The project followed a public protest after the broadcasting of a popular TV mini-series "Holocaust" that, in Polish American opinion, portrayed Poles unfairly. The project was inaugurated by a technical workshop for interviewers and a public forum. The purpose of both was to emphasize the issue of complexity of the Holocaust, publicize the project, and locate additional survivors.
Between 1980 and 1981 four interviewers - Prof. Stanislaus Blejwas, Dr. M.B. Biskupski, Mrs. Aleksandra Nowakowska, and Mr. Joseph Jedynak - conducted and recorded interviews with 32 Polish gentiles, survivors of Nazi concentration camps. The interviews were broadcasted by the Connecticut Public Radio in 5-part series in April 1982. The tapes were later transcribed.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
Collection includes documentation of the project, original tapes, transcription of tapes and English translation if necessary. Also included in the collection are materials describing various Polish American initiatives that aimed at educating American public opinion about Polish losses during WWII and Polish-Jewish relations during the war.
The collection is open for research.
Material in the collection was donated by Prof. Stanislaus A. Blejwas.
Search Terms
Stanislaus A. Blejwas; John P. Wodarski; Holocaust survivors; Holocaust survivors -- Interviews; Holocaust Survivors -- Connecticut; Holocaust Survivors -- Connecticut -- New Britain.; Oral histories; Sound recordings; Pamphlets; Photographs; Clippings
Arrangement
The Collection is kept in the original arrangement it was received.
Container List
[The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.]
- Polish survivors of the Holocaust - proposal, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Polish survivors of the Holocaust - grant correspondence, funds, reports, 1980-1982 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Polish survivors of the Holocaust - correspondence in support of the project, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Polish survivors of the Holocaust - correspondence, 1980-1984 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Polish survivors of the Holocaust - gifts and matching funds, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Polish survivors of the Holocaust - publicity, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Polish survivors of the Holocaust - interim reports and final report by project director Prof. Stanislaus Blejwas, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Polish Survivors of the Holocaust - forms, permissions from participants, correspondence and notes related to interview participation or decline, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Polish survivors of the Holocaust - bibliography and workshop, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Polish survivors of the Holocaust - applications for interviewers and administrative assistant, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Polish survivors of the Holocaust - evaluation of the project by Prof. William V. D'Antonio, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Polish Survivors of the Holocaust - ledger with letters, notes from meetings, receipts and payments, 1980-1982 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- World War II and Poland a public forum at Central Connecticut State College - "The Holocaust in literature" a lecture by Lothar Kahn, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- World War II and Poland a public forum at Central Connecticut State College - "Poles and Jews" and "The Camps", two lectures by Stephen M. Berk (includes audiotape), 1980 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- World War II and Poland a public forum at Central Connecticut State College - "Occupied Warsaw" lecture by Lucjan Dobroszycki (audiotape), 1980 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- The movie "Holocaust" and Poles and Jews during World War II, television program, September, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- The movie "Holocaust" and Poles and Jews during World War II, television program - reaction from Polish community, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- "Holocaust illiteracy" essay by Prof. Stanislaus A. Blejwas and related clippings, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Irene Pruszynska Ogden - letter and clippings about her father Kazimierz Proszynski and his experience in the concentration camps, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Dokumenty Zbrodni Hitlerowskich, by Kazimierz Goncwol (photocopy), [1945?] (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Polish Survivors of the Holocaust - handwritten list of people interviewed for the project, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Polish Survivors of the Holocaust - reasons for participation in the project, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Adamus Stephan - interview in Polish and handwritten notes, April, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Amendola, Anna - interview in English, related correspondence and handwritten notes., October, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Bieganski, Stefan - interview in Polish, May 1981 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Cierpikowski, Henry - only notes in English, February, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Depa, Frederic - interview in Polish and notes in English, October, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Drelichowski, Piotr - interview in Polish and English translation, November, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Fikus, Witold - interview in Polish and English translation, related correspondence and notes, October, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Gelissen (Kornriech), Regina - interview in English with notes, November, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Gulak, Franciszek - interview in Polish, December, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Hamaluk, Wanda and Tadeusz - interview in English and notes, December, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Jakubowska (Lukaszek), Aniela - handwritten notes in English, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Kejna, Wincenty - interview in Polish and English translation, October, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Klos, Bronislaw - interview in Polish, English translation and notes, May, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Kozlowski, Ludwik - interview in Polish, notes in English, May, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Kukiz, Gustaw, Wlodzimierz - copies of documents related to imprisonment in concentration camp, no interview., 1980 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Kwiecien, Stanislaw - interview in Polish, English translation, photographs and clippings from., 1980 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Lausch, Wlodzimierz - handwritten notes from interview., 1980 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Mleczko, Francis - interview in Polish, English translation and notes, April, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Mroz, Jozef - interview in English, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Powidzki, Edwarda - interview in English., 1980 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Ruminski, Edmund - interview in Polish, English translation and notes., November, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Sadanowicz, Jan A. - interview in English., November, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Sieklicki, Stanislaw - written memoirs, no interview., 1983 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Sikorska, Krystyna - interview in English and notes, April, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Siwinski, Stefan - interview in Polish, English translation, November, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Sosnowski, Henryk - interview in Polish, English translation, April, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Stec, Maria - interview in Polish, November, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Strojny, Felicja - interview in English and notes, March, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Szymerski, Jan - interview in Polish, English translation and notes, October, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Tarlowska, Irena - interview in Polish, partial translation in English and notes, March, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Wardzala, Joseph - interview in Polish, translation in english and notes, October, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Wawrowski, Stefan - copies of written memoirs in Polish, camp documents in German (copies), notes in English, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Ziembinski, Marian - interview in Polish, March, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Arrests (fragments of interviews). (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Slave labor (fragments of interviews). (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Camps - transport, arrival and quarantine (fragments of interviews). (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Camps - moral behavior (fragments of interviews). (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Camps - religious values faith and hope (fragments of interviews). (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Camps - outside aid (fragments of interviews). (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Camps - sources of information (fragments of interviews). (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Camps - resistance and executions (fragments of interviews). (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Camps - population, difference of treatment, discipline (fragments of interviews). (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Camps - exterminations, awarness of Jews as primary victims (fragments of interviews). (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Camps - friendship and survival (fragments of interviews). (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Camps - prison staff (fragments of interviews). (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Camps - hospitals (fragments of interviews). (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Camps - organizing efforts to help others (fragments of interviews). (Box 6, Folder 14)
- Camps - work conditions (fragments of interviews). (Box 6, Folder 15)
- Camps - hygiene (fragments of interviews). (Box 6, Folder 16)
- Camps - roll-calls (fragments of interviews). (Box 6, Folder 17)
- Camps - abuse of prisoners (fragments of interviews). (Box 6, Folder 18)
- Camps - work (fragments of interviews) (Box 6, Folder 19)
- Camps - food (fragments of interviews) (Box 6, Folder 20)
- Camps - general conditions (fragments of interviews) (Box 6, Folder 21)
- Camps - exit from camps, last month of war (fragments of interviews) (Box 6, Folder 22)
- Camps - liberation (fragments of interviews) (Box 6, Folder 23)
- Camps - life after liberation (fragments of interviews) (Box 6, Folder 24)
- Camps - various topics (fragments of interviews) (Box 6, Folder 25)
- Camps - conditions in other camps (fragments of interviews) (Box 6, Folder 26)
- Handwritten notes from interviews and other publications related to concentration camps (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Handwritten notes on arrival at camps (Box 7, Folder 2)
- War and occupation - notes from interviews (Box 7, Folder 3)
- War and occupation and biographical sketches of participants in the project (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Polish Survivors of the Holocaust project - proposal to broadcast it on Connecticut Public Radio and related correspondence, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Polish Survivors of the Holocaust project - Connecticut Public Radio broadcast, Programs 1-5 (hardcopy and audiotapes) (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Survivors of the WWII concentration camps - field research proposal by Krystyna Zamorska, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 7)
- First Poles in KL Auschwitz, essay in Polish by Irena Strzelecka (photocopy) (Box 7, Folder 8)
- "Smoke over Birkenau" by Seweryna Szmaglewska (photocopy), 1947 (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Maximillian Kolbe - clippings, articles, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 10)
- "Forgotten voices - Holocaust illiteracy" by Stanislaus A. Blejwas, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Jewish survivors in Connecticut - letters, clippings, 1981-1985 (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Holocaust literature and course guides, related correspondence (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Holocaust literature, articles, pamphlets, clippings, 1981-1984 (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Holocaust media - Docu-drama concept (clippings), 1981-1986 (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Holocaust media - "Holocaust" (clippings), 1978-1983 (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Holocaust media - "Escape from Sobibor" (clippings), 1987 (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Holocaust media - "Lena" press release from Polish American Congress, 1987 (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Holocaust media - "Shoah" (clippings), 1986-1987 (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Holocaust media - "Shoah", correspondence and Polish community reactions, 1986-1987 (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Holocaust media - "Sophie's Choice" clippings, 1978-11983 (Box 8, Folder 11)
- Holocaust media - "Sophie's Choice" Polish American Historical Association symposium, December, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 12)
- Holocaust media - "The Winds of War" clippings, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 13)
- Holocaust - President's Commission on the Holocaust report, 1979 (Box 8, Folder 14)
- Holocaust - President Reagan's visit to Bergen-Belsen concentration camp and Bitburg cemetery in Germany (clippings), 1985 (Box 8, Folder 15)
- Holocaust - US Holocaust Memorial Council, pamphlets, 1984 (Box 8, Folder 16)
- Holocaust - war criminals (clippings), 1981-1984 (Box 8, Folder 17)
- Holocaust survivors (clippings), 1979-1985 (Box 8, Folder 18)
- Holocaust - "Polish Death Camps" issue (clippings), 1980-1987 (Box 8, Folder 19)
- Holocaust - conferences and dialogues, 1984-1986 (Box 8, Folder 20)
- Holocaust - "The Trees of Warsaw" article by A.M. Rosenthal, NY Times Magazine, August, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 21)
- Holocaust - Poles and Jews various articles and responses, 1974-1984 (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Holocaust - Polish American response, gentile survivors, 1980-1984 (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Holocaust - various articles written by Eugene Kusielewicz related to Holocaust, 1984-1986 (Box 9, Folder 3)
- Holocaust - Righteous Gentiles, 1951-1984 (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Holocaust - Polish Jewish relations articles by Prof. Ronald Modras, 1981-1985 (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Holocaust - Polish Jewish relations articles from newspapers Zgoda and Nowy Dziennik, 1988 (Box 9, Folder 6)
- Holocaust - Response from the Polish American community: book by Richard Lukas "Forgotten Holocaust", 1980-1984 (Box 9, Folder 7)
- Holocaust - Response from the Polish American community: article by W.S. Maliszewski, July, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 8)
- Holocaust - Response from the Polish American community: Polish American Congress Anti-Bigotry Committee, 1974-1986 (Box 9, Folder 9)
- Holocaust - Response from the Polish American community: Holocaust Remembrance Day, New Britain, 1979 (Box 9, Folder 10)
- Holocaust - Response from the Polish American community in New Jersey, 1986-1989 (Box 9, Folder 11)
- Holocaust - Response from the Polish American community: Essays by Rev. John Pawlikowski, 1979-1987 (Box 9, Folder 12)
- Holocaust - Response from the Polish American community: Polish American-Jewish American Task Force, 1983-1986 (Box 9, Folder 13)
- Holocaust - Response from the Polish American community: Polish Association of Former Political Prisoners, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 14)
- Holocaust - Response from the Polish American community: Polish Institute of Arts and Science panel discussion reaction to the movie "Sophie's Choice", 1983 (Box 9, Folder 15)
- Holocaust - Response from the Polish American community from Western Massachusetts, 1987 (Box 9, Folder 16)
- Holocaust - Response from the Polish American community from California, 1982-1989 (Box 9, Folder 17)
- Holocaust - Response from the Polish American community: correspondence with Waclaw Zajaczkowski, 1977-1984 (Box 9, Folder 18)
- Holocaust - Response from the Polish American community: correspondence with Eugene Slotkowski, clippings and articles, 1977-1987 (Box 9, Folder 18)
- Holocaust - Response from the Polish American community: correspondence with Edwin Kulawiec, 1980-1983 (Box 9, Folder 19)
- Holocaust - John Paul II (clippings>, 1985-1986 (Box 9, Folder 20)
- Kosciuszko Foundation lecture series on Poles and Jews and the Holocaust, 1985 (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Kosciuszko Foundation flier for the summer session in Poland, Polish Jewish relations, 1987 (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Kosciuszko Foundation, NY Metropolitan chapter - correspondence related to Poles and Christians during the Holocaust, 1983-1987 (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Teaching about the Holocaust and Genocide, NY State Department of Education, 1st draft, 1983 (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Teaching about the Holocaust and Genocide, NY State Department of Education, 3rd draft, v.1, 1984 (Box 10, Folder 5)
- Teaching about the Holocaust and Genocide, NY State Department of Education, 3rd draft, v.2, 1984 (Box 10, Folder 6)
- The Holocaust and Genocide, Stated Department of Education, critical annotations, 1983 (Box 10, Folder 7)
- Polish victims of the Holocaust and Genocide: towards an objective view, symposium at Seton Hall University, Polish American Congress, NJ, 1985 (Box 10, Folder 8)
- Polish Holocaust Commemorative Committee, Rhode Island, 1983 (Box 10, Folder 9)
- Genocide of the Poles, an article by Michal Zawadzki (California), 1987 (Box 10, Folder 10)
- Committee on Holocaust awareness, Connecticut - news releases, publications, flyers, 1980 (Box 10, Folder 11)
- Teaching the Holocaust and Genocide, articles in: Religious Education; The History Teacher, 1980, 1983 (Box 10, Folder 12)
- Polish Survivors of the Holocaust - this box contains audiotapes with interviews of participants in the project. Tapes were converted to CD. (Box 11, Folder 1)